<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ruleset id="azure-keystore-certificates"
         xmlns="http://windup.jboss.org/schema/jboss-ruleset"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://windup.jboss.org/schema/jboss-ruleset http://windup.jboss.org/schema/jboss-ruleset/windup-jboss-ruleset.xsd">
    <metadata>
        <description>
            Detect JKS files and certificates
        </description>
        <dependencies>
            <addon id="org.jboss.windup.rules,windup-rules-xml,3.0.0.Final"/>
        </dependencies>
        <targetTechnology id="azure-spring-apps"/>
        <targetTechnology id="azure-appservice"/>
        <targetTechnology id="azure-aks"/>
        <targetTechnology id="azure-container-apps"/>
        <tag>JKS</tag>
    </metadata>
    <rules>
        <rule id="azure-keystore-certificates-01000">
            <when>
                <file filename="{*}.jks"/>
            </when>
            <perform>
                <hint title="Java KeyStore file found" effort="3" category-id="potential">
                    <message>
                        The application has a Java KeyStore file. You can migrate it to Azure Key Vault.

                        * **Migrate the Java KeyStore to Azure Key Vault**: With Azure Key Vault you can centralize and securely manage your cryptographic keys and certificates in a highly available and scalable service. Azure Key Vault provides robust access control and auditing capabilities, ensuring that your keys and certificates are protected and accessible only to authorized entities.
                        
                        * **Update your Java application**: Modify your Java application's code to retrieve the keys and certificates from Azure Key Vault. Update the code that references the Java KeyStore to use Azure Key Vault APIs for accessing the cryptographic materials.
                        
                        * **Secure access to Azure Key Vault**: Configure appropriate access policies and permissions for your Azure Key Vault to ensure that only authorized users and applications can access the keys and certificates stored in it.
                    </message>
                    <link title="Azure Key Vault" href="https://azure.microsoft.com/products/key-vault/"/>
                    <link title="Azure Key Vault documentation" href="https://learn.microsoft.com/azure/key-vault/"/>
                </hint>
            </perform>
        </rule>
        <rule id="azure-keystore-certificates-02000">
            <when>
                <or>
                    <javaclass references="java.security.KeyStore.getInstance({*})">
                        <location>METHOD_CALL</location>
                    </javaclass>
                    <javaclass references="java.security.KeyStore.load({*})">
                        <location>METHOD_CALL</location>
                    </javaclass>
                </or>
            </when>
            <perform>
                <hint title="The application loads certificates into a KeyStore" effort="3" category-id="potential">
                    <message>
                        The application loads a KeyStore from a file or an input stream. To migrate this code to Azure, you would need to modify it so it retrieves the cryptographic material from Azure Key Vault instead.

                        * **Create an Azure Key Vault**: Azure Key Vault is a secure storage service that allows you to store and manage cryptographic keys, secrets, and certificates.

                        * **Import keys and certificates into Azure Key Vault**: Use the Azure Key Vault Java SDK or Azure CLI to import the keys and certificates into Azure Key Vault. Create corresponding key and certificate objects in Azure Key Vault and import the key material and certificates obtained from the existing KeyStore.

                        * **Update your Java code**: Modify your Java code that to retrieve the cryptographic material from Azure Key Vault. Instead of loading from a file or input stream, use the Azure Key Vault Java SDK to access the keys and certificates stored in Azure Key Vault. Update the code to authenticate and retrieve the cryptographic material using Azure.
                    </message>
                    <link title="Azure Key Vault" href="https://azure.microsoft.com/products/key-vault/"/>
                    <link title="Azure Key Vault documentation" href="https://learn.microsoft.com/azure/key-vault/"/>
                    <link title="Azure Key Vault JCA client library for Java" href="https://learn.microsoft.com/java/api/overview/azure/security-keyvault-jca-readme"/>
                    <link title="Azure Key Vault Certificate client library for Java" href="https://learn.microsoft.com/java/api/overview/azure/security-keyvault-certificates-readme"/>
                </hint>
            </perform>
        </rule>
    </rules>
</ruleset>
